For years, the Transformer architecture and its self-attention
mechanism have reigned supreme in deep learning. However,
as sequence lengths scale, self-attention's quadratic computational complexity
presents a critical bottleneck. State Space Models, or
SSMs, have emerged as a powerful alternative, offering
linear-time complexity with respect to sequence length while
maintaining competitive performance. Grounded in classical control theory,
these models map a continuous input sequence to
a continuous output sequence through a hidden state
space. By combining the training efficiency of parallelizable
convolutions with the inference speed of recurrent models,
modern SSMs are redefining the frontier of sequence
modeling. Let's explore the mathematical foundation that makes
this linear-time scaling possible.
At the core of state space models are
continuous-time differential equations. An input signal u of
t is mapped to an output signal y
of t by first projecting the input into
an N-dimensional latent state x of t. Mathematically,
the derivative of x with respect to t
is equal to matrix A times x of
t plus matrix B times u of t.
The output y of t is then computed
as matrix C times x of t. To
process digital data, these continuous equations must be
discretized using a step size delta. Through bilinear
discretization or zero-order hold, the continuous matrices are
transformed into discrete matrices A-bar and B-bar. This
allows the model to be computed either recurrently
for ultra-fast, constant-time inference, or convolutionally as a
single parallel pass during training.
While classical SSMs like S4 excel at long-range
dependencies, they struggle with content-dependent reasoning tasks because
their transition matrices are static and independent of
the input tokens. Mamba, introduced by Gu and
Dao, addresses this limitation by making the discretization
step delta, and the projection matrices B and
C, dynamic functions of the input token at
each step. This input-dependent selectivity allows the model
to selectively remember or forget information along the
sequence. However, dynamic matrices break the convolutional parallelization
property. To maintain training efficiency, Mamba leverages a
hardware-aware parallel associative scan, streaming intermediate states directly
through fast GPU SRAM and avoiding slow off-chip
memory write-backs.
Building on Mamba, Mamba-2 introduces Structured State Space
Duality, or SSD, which establishes a formal mathematical
connection between selective SSMs and attention mechanisms. SSD
shows that selective SSMs can be cast as
semi-separable matrices, which compute a form of linear
attention where the key-value states are decayed over
time by the transition matrix. By framing SSMs
as dual attention formulations, Mamba-2 enables the use
of tensor parallelism and highly optimized matrix multiplication
kernels. This dual framework achieves two to eight
times faster training and inference throughput compared to
Mamba-1, merging the theoretical scaling benefits of state
space models with the hardware efficiency of attention.
The evolution from standard self-attention to Structured State
Space Duality marks a profound shift in sequence
representation. By combining linear time and space complexity
with dynamic, content-dependent selectivity, Mamba and Mamba-2 offer
a scalable alternative to traditional Transformers for long-context
applications. To continue exploring the mathematical details and
physical hardware co-designs behind modern AI, subscribe to
Gemini three point five Flash Model. Let's keep
optimizing the future of computation.