Here is a puzzle.
An AI model is asked to grade four essays.
One of them, it secretly wrote itself.
If it gives that essay a higher
score than the other judges do, you might call that bias.
But what exactly is the bias about?
Is the AI scoring it higher because it wrote it?
Or because it thinks it wrote it?
In other words, is the bias about authorship, or about belief?
This sounds like a hair-splitting distinction.
It is not.
The two questions point at completely different
ways AI judges could be biased.
If the bias is about authorship,
then writing style is doing the work.
The model recognizes its own fingerprints — its phrasings,
its rhythms — and rewards them,
whether or not it consciously knows the essay is its own.
If the bias is about belief,
then a kind of metacognitive label is doing the work.
The model decides "this is mine," and
that single decision raises the score.
One bias rides on style.
The other rides on a guess.
They have very different fixes.
We ran an experiment with four frontier models — Claude,
Gemini, GPT, and Kimi — across forty cases.
In each case, a model wrote an answer,
and a model graded it,
with no labels showing who wrote what.
After grading, the judge made a separate
guess about who had written each answer.
That gives us, for every score, two yes-or-no flags.
One: was the judge actually the author?
Two: did the judge believe it was the author?
Now we can ask which flag predicts the score.
We fit a simple model.
Score equals an intercept, plus a coefficient for actual self,
plus a coefficient for perceived self,
plus controls for which judge and which prompt.
The coefficient on actual self is minus
zero point three five, with a confidence interval that touches zero.
In words: when we hold belief fixed,
actually being the author does basically nothing.
The coefficient on perceived self is plus
one point five three, with a confidence
interval that clears zero by a comfortable margin.
In words: when we hold authorship fixed,
believing you are the author adds about
one and a half points to the score,
on a ten point scale.
Belief is the entire effect.
Authorship, on its own, is not.
This number is real, but you should
know where the leverage is.
Three of the four judges — Claude,
GPT, and most of Gemini — are
very good at recognizing their own writing.
For them, "is the author" and "thinks
it is the author" move together.
They cannot tell us, by themselves,
which of the two matters more.
Kimi is different.
Kimi never correctly recognizes its own writing
— zero out of ten on its own work.
And on a handful of other models' answers,
Kimi guesses "I wrote this." That gives
us four cells where the two flags disagree.
Those four cells are where belief and authorship get separated.
Here is Kimi's grid.
When the answer was actually Kimi's,
and Kimi did not recognize it,
the average score was five point seven four.
When the answer was someone else's,
and Kimi mistakenly thought it was its own,
the average score was nine point one zero.
Same judge.
Same grading rubric.
Different cell — and a gap of more than three points.
The thing that moved was not the writing.
It was the label Kimi put on
the writing in its head.
It is one judge.
So we have to be careful.
Gemini, the other judge with a few misrecognitions,
actually shows the opposite within-judge pattern —
when Gemini thinks an answer is its own,
it tends to score it a little lower than baseline.
But pool the regression across all four judges,
and the perceived-self coefficient still comes out clearly positive,
because Kimi's gap is larger in magnitude
and points the same way as the
dominant story for the other models.
The honest version of the headline is this.
Among the judges that can separate the two effects,
belief moves the score by a lot more than authorship does.
The earlier, three-judge version of this study
— without Kimi — could not see this at all.
Step back.
In an earlier video on this channel,
we showed that when you attach a
name label to an answer, the label itself biases the judge.
That was the experimental version of the
story — change the label, watch the score move.
This is the natural version.
Even without any label, judges still form
a belief about authorship — and that
belief is the channel the bias travels through.
It is not style recognition reaching into the rating.
It is a self-attribution flag setting the rating.
If you are using one AI to grade another's output,
the implication is uncomfortable but useful.
Hiding the author label is not enough.
You also need to take care that
the judge cannot easily guess who the author is.
Paraphrasing, style normalization, or routing answers through
a translator first — interventions that target the perception,
not the authorship — should reduce this
kind of self-preference more than interventions that only hide labels.
You are debiasing the belief, not the signature.
When a model favors its own work,
the bias does not live in the words it produces.
It lives in the moment the judge
decides whose work it is looking at.
Belief beats authorship.
The label your model puts on the
page in its own head is doing
more work than anything actually on the page.
If you want a less biased AI judge, start there.