Have you ever wondered why generating text
with large language models feels so sluggish?
A seventy-billion parameter model seems to crawl,
outputting just a few words per second.
You might think the GPU is working at full capacity,
burning through complex mathematical equations.
But the truth is, the GPU is actually idling.
It is trapped behind a physical barrier
known as the memory bandwidth bottleneck.
Today, we will explore Speculative Decoding: the brilliant,
mathematically rigorous algorithm that breaks this bottleneck
to speed up LLM inference by two to three times,
with absolutely zero loss in quality.
To understand why LLMs are slow,
we have to look at arithmetic intensity.
In standard autoregressive generation, a model produces text token-by-token.
To generate a single token,
the GPU must load every single parameter
of the model from High Bandwidth Memory,
or HBM, into the fast on-chip SRAM cache.
For a seventy-billion parameter model,
that means transferring one hundred and forty
gigabytes of data across the memory bus
just to calculate a single word.
Because memory transfer is orders of magnitude
slower than arithmetic computation, the GPU cores
spend over ninety percent of their time sitting idle,
waiting for data.
Standard generation is completely memory-bandwidth bound.
How do we solve a physical hardware
bottleneck with a clever software algorithm?
The answer is Speculative Decoding.
Imagine you need to write a highly technical report.
Instead of having a senior researcher draft it word-by-word,
you hire a fast junior writer to draft several paragraphs.
The senior researcher then reviews the draft in a single,
swift sweep, correcting any mistakes, but accepting everything that looks correct.
In the AI world, we use a tiny,
fast draft model to speculate several candidate tokens,
and a large, slow target model to
verify them all in parallel.
Here is how the collaboration works in detail.
First, we run the small draft model autoregressively for K steps.
Because the draft model has far fewer parameters,
it can load its weights and generate candidate tokens extremely quickly.
For example, if K equals four,
the draft model rapidly generates four candidate tokens, one after another.
These tokens are cheap to produce,
but they are just educated guesses.
They might contain grammatical errors or misinterpret the prompt,
so they cannot be trusted blindly.
Next comes the masterstroke.
We feed the prompt and all four
draft tokens into the large target model simultaneously.
Normally, running the target model four times
would take four slow memory load cycles.
But because the draft tokens are already written,
we can process them in a single parallel forward pass.
The target model computes the exact probability
distributions for all four positions at once.
We have traded serial memory accesses for
a single parallel computation, fully utilizing the GPU's idle compute cores.
Now, how does the target model decide
which draft tokens to accept?
We cannot just accept tokens where the target model agrees,
because that would alter the final probability
distribution and degrade model quality.
Instead, we use a stochastic acceptance algorithm.
For each draft token, we compare the target model's probability,
P, to the draft model's probability, Q.
If the target model's probability is greater
than or equal to the draft model's, we accept the token.
If it is lower, we accept it
stochastically based on their ratio,
keeping the final output mathematically identical to the target model alone.
What happens when a draft token is rejected?
Suppose the first two tokens are accepted,
but the third is rejected.
We immediately discard the third and fourth tokens.
But we do not go home empty-handed.
In the same parallel forward pass where
the target model verified the draft,
it also calculated the true probability distribution
for the next token at the rejection point.
We sample from this corrected distribution to
get a brand new, verified token on the spot.
In this single step, we successfully generated
three verified tokens while only loading the large model's weights once.
Behind the scenes, we also have to
manage the model's memory state: the Key-Value, or KV, cache.
The KV cache stores past key and
value vectors to prevent redundant calculations in future steps.
When the draft model speculates tokens,
both the draft and target models update their KV caches.
But when a rejection occurs, those speculative cache entries become invalid.
The algorithm must dynamically roll back the
KV caches of both models,
pruning the entries corresponding to the discarded
tokens so that the next round of
speculation starts with a perfectly clean history.
The performance impact of speculative decoding is staggering.
In practice, draft models achieve high acceptance rates,
often accepting three to four tokens per draft cycle.
This translates to a direct two to
three times speedup in wall-clock latency.
And because the stochastic verification math is exact,
the output is guaranteed to be identical
to what the large target model would
have produced on its own.
It is a pure win: faster response times,
lower hardware costs, and absolutely zero compromise on quality.
Speculative Decoding teaches us a profound lesson about modern artificial intelligence.
We do not always need faster transistors
or bigger chips to build faster systems.
By understanding the physical layout of our
hardware and designing algorithms that align with its strengths,
we can unlock massive performance gains.
If you enjoyed this deep dive into
the engineering of speed, subscribe to Gemini
three point five Flash Model for more insights.
Remember: true optimization isn't just about raw horsepower—it's about working smarter.