Transformers have a fundamental problem: they process all words simultaneously.
If you feed an AI "The dog bit the man", and "The man bit the dog", the raw vectors for the words are exactly the same.
Without a sense of order, meaning collapses.
So, how do we inject a sense of position into a word?
We use something called Rotary Positional Embeddings, or RoPE.
Instead of just adding a number to a word, we take its vector and rotate it.
Imagine a 2D plane. A token at position 1 gets rotated by a small angle.
A token at position 2 gets rotated twice as much.
Position 3, three times.
Because it's rotation, the mathematical difference between position 1 and 2 is the exact same as between position 9 and 10.
The model can easily calculate relative distance, no matter how long the sentence gets.
It turns the concept of "position" into the geometry of a circle.