If one AI judge plays favorites,
the obvious fix is to use more judges.
Average across a panel, let the bias wash out.
The crowd corrects the individual.
It's such a clean idea that a
lot of AI evaluation pipelines just assume it works.
So we tested it.
Across four frontier models scoring forty responses,
here's how much bias disappears as you
grow the panel from one judge to four.
And here's where it stops.
The experiment is the same one I've
been talking about in this series.
Four frontier AI models — Claude,
Gemini, GPT, and Kimi — each wrote
ten responses to a shared prompt set,
and each then graded every response from
every author on a five-rubric scale.
Forty responses, four judges, blinded labels.
From that grid we can build any panel we like.
A single judge.
A pair.
A trio.
Or all four.
And for each panel we can compute
one number: how much higher does a
response score when its author is on the panel,
compared to when the author is not?
The hope is dilution.
If each judge has their own quirky
bias and the quirks aren't correlated,
then averaging more judges should shrink the bias toward zero.
That's the wisdom-of-crowds argument applied to AI evaluation.
So we enumerated every panel: four panels of size one,
six panels of size two,
four panels of size three, and one panel of size four.
For each, we measured the self-versus-peer gap, with bootstrap confidence intervals.
Two thousand resamples.
Let's see what the dilution curve actually looks like.
At panel size one, the mean self-versus-peer
gap across the four judges is plus zero point three eight.
That's small only because it's a mean.
The individual judges range from plus two
point four to minus two point nine.
At size two, the panel mean is
plus zero point one nine.
At size three, plus zero point one three.
And at size four — the full
panel of all four judges — the
residual self-influence is plus zero point zero nine,
with a ninety-five percent confidence interval from
plus zero point zero four to plus zero point one five.
So yes, the bias shrinks.
But the confidence interval at size four does not include zero.
That's the headline.
Even when you average across all four frontier AI judges,
the author's own vote still tilts the
panel consensus by about a tenth of a point.
It's a small effect.
But it is statistically nonzero,
and it is the floor of what
a four-model ensemble can give you.
There is no magic in adding a
fifth judge if that fifth judge is also an author.
Every model brings its own opinions about its own work,
and on average those opinions are warmer than the peers'.
The crowd shrinks the bias.
It does not erase it.
But the mean across panels hides something
much more important than the dilution curve.
The panels of size two are a clean illustration.
The Claude plus GPT panel shows plus
two point five eight — both judges are pro-author,
their biases compound.
The Gemini plus Kimi panel shows minus
two point zero seven — one mild
self-favorer and one anti-self model, and the net is sharply negative.
The Claude plus Kimi panel is roughly
neutral at minus zero point eight.
Same panel size, three completely different verdicts.
Which judges you pick matters more than how many.
So if adding judges doesn't reach zero, what does?
The answer is structural.
Look at the panels of size three
that do not contain the author of the response.
There, the residual bias is essentially indistinguishable from zero.
Translation: the cure isn't more judges in general.
The cure is excluding the author from their own jury.
Peer-only review.
As soon as the author is sitting on the panel,
even diluted among three peers, the score still leans their way.
This sounds like a small methodological point.
It isn't.
A lot of how AI systems get
evaluated today involves AI judges.
Preference data for fine-tuning.
Best-of-N reranking, where a model generates several
candidates and picks its favorite.
Leaderboard evaluations that ask a strong model to grade other models.
In many of these setups,
the model being trained or evaluated is also on the panel.
That residual plus zero point one tilt
is the tax you pay for letting the author vote.
It's small per evaluation, but it compounds
across the millions of comparisons that shape a model.
Some caveats.
The bias we're measuring is a within-judge
gap on forty responses, not the absolute quality of any model.
Panel composition effects are larger than panel-size effects,
which means in practice the choice of
which judges you trust matters enormously.
Kimi's anti-self behavior actually pulls panels down,
which is unusual and may not generalize.
And the residual of plus zero point
one at full panel may shrink further with more authors.
So this is a floor estimate, not a universal constant.
The structural point — exclude the author — survives those caveats.
The wisdom of crowds works on AI judges, partly.
Going from one judge to four shrinks
the average self-preference bias by about three quarters.
But the last bit doesn't melt away
by adding more of the same.
To get all the way to zero
you need a different rule: the author
is not on the jury.
Peer review, structurally.
The cure for self-preference isn't more judges.
It's the right ones.