If you asked an artificial intelligence to
grade its own writing, you'd probably expect
it to be a little generous with itself.
Most of them are.
But one of them isn't.
One of them looks at its own
work and gives it lower marks than anyone else does.
So here's the question.
Is that AI being unusually honest?
Or is it just genuinely worse?
We ran a study where four AI models — Claude,
Gemini, GPT, and Kimi — each wrote
answers to the same set of prompts,
and then each model graded all four sets of answers.
Including its own.
This gives us a clean way to measure self-preference.
Compare the score a model gives its
own answer to the score the other
three judges give that same answer.
The gap is the favoritism.
Three of the four models behaved the way you'd expect.
Claude rated its own writing about two
and a half points higher than its peers did.
GPT, about one and a third points higher.
Gemini, a smaller but still positive bump
of two thirds of a point.
Different sizes, same direction.
Self-flattery in three different shades.
Then there's Kimi.
Kimi rated its own writing nearly three
full points lower than the other judges did.
A self-preference score of minus two point eight seven.
This is the opposite of every other model.
On a coin that has self-love on one side,
Kimi landed on the other.
There are two ways to read this.
Maybe Kimi is the most honest evaluator in the group,
willing to give itself the low marks
the others can't bring themselves to.
Or maybe Kimi's own answers really are weaker,
and Kimi simply has better judgment about its own quality.
We can actually tell the two apart with the data.
Here's the tell.
Look at how the other three judges scored Kimi's answers.
The average is around five point two,
on a ten point scale.
The other three models' answers,
scored by the same judges, sit between eight and nine.
This is not a close call.
The peer consensus is that Kimi's answers
genuinely score lower in this evaluation setup.
The other judges aren't being mean.
They agree across the board.
So Kimi's low self-score isn't humility.
It's largely accuracy.
Kimi can see the same quality gap that everyone else sees.
We can go one level deeper.
Break the scores down by rubric and
the gap concentrates in one place.
On the criterion called constraint adherence — basically,
did the answer follow the format the
prompt asked for — Kimi penalizes itself by almost five points.
And by task category, the gap is
biggest in logic and math.
Five and a half points lower on logic.
Four and a half lower on math.
On softer prose tasks, the gap is small.
This isn't a global sense of inadequacy.
It's targeted.
Kimi is, in this setup,
weaker on the strict-format tasks, and Kimi knows it.
Now the part that complicates the honesty story.
If Kimi were simply unbiased,
you'd expect its scores of the other
three models to be even-handed.
They aren't.
When we measure Kimi's biases toward the other three models,
one of them stands out.
Kimi has a measurable preference for Claude.
Plus three tenths of a point,
every time Claude's name is in the byline.
So Kimi isn't bias-free.
Kimi is differently biased.
Less self-love, but a soft spot for one of its peers.
This is the lesson worth holding onto.
Self-preference and accuracy are not opposites.
A model can rate itself low because
it really is weaker, and a model
can rate itself high because it really is stronger,
and in both cases the score has
nothing to do with honesty.
What gives the bias away is the structure of the errors.
Where does the over-scoring happen.
Which peers does the model lean toward.
What kinds of tasks bring the gap out.
When you see one model behave dramatically
differently from the others in an evaluation,
the temptation is to call it the honest one.
The contrarian.
The truth-teller.
Sometimes that's right.
More often, the outlier just has a
different mix of strengths, weaknesses,
and quiet preferences than the rest of the group.
The interesting models aren't the ones who like themselves more.
They're the ones whose errors give away their structure.
The full study, with all the data, is linked below.
Thanks for watching.