When you type a word into an AI,
it doesn't see letters. It sees numbers. Specifically,
coordinates. To an AI, every concept in the
universe is mapped to a physical location in
a vast, mathematical landscape. We call this: Latent
Space.
Imagine a simple map with just two dimensions.
Size, and fluffiness. By mapping concepts to coordinates,
the AI begins to understand relationships. A kitten
is closer to a bear in fluffiness, but
closer to an ant in size. The distance
between points is the meaning.
But reality is infinitely more complex than two
dimensions. So, we add a third axis. Let's
call it danger. Now our concepts are suspended
in 3D space.
Modern AI models like the one you chat
with don't use three dimensions. They use thousands.
Sometimes over four thousand different directions to measure
every subtle nuance of human language. Tone, grammar,
sarcasm, historical context. All of it is mapped
as coordinates in a massive, hyper-dimensional space. We
can't picture a 4000-dimensional space, but the math
still works exactly the same.
And because meaning is just math, the AI
can do algebra with concepts. If you find
the distance and direction that takes you from
"Man" to "Woman"... ...and you apply that exact
same movement starting from "King", you land directly
on "Queen".
It isn't thinking in words. It's navigating a
galaxy of meaning, plotting a course from one
coordinate to the next. The next time an
AI writes you a poem or solves a
coding problem, remember: it's just drawing lines in
the dark.